this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is Keisha Padilla
for software engineering radio today's
episode is about engineering impact in
measuring productivity with Travis
Kimmel Travis is the CEO of get prime a
SAS company offering engineering
productivity measurement as a service
with a mission to bring visibility into
software development process and bridge
the communication gap between
engineering and stakeholders
Travis is also involved with a lot of
community work in technology space
welcome to software engineering video
Travis thanks it's great to be here so
today we are going to talk about
engineering productivity in metrics and
specifically learn from your experience
Travis working with the engineering
teams before and now with Kate prime
generally all the meaningful insights
for the teams and business stakeholders
measuring value in productivity so let's
start with some background establishing
the theme well in your blog you talked a
lot about engineering in fact we're
going to understand more about the
common theme and then you know hopefully
you can share your experience and
thoughts on metrics driven engineering
management with our listeners but first
what has really changed in IT and
specifically software engineering world
to even have this like renewed emphasis
on measurement yeah that's a great
question you know I think one of the
things that we've seen served over the
last 10 15 years is that almost every
industry has been as moved towards
quantification right so if you if you if
you've been in a board meeting you see
these you'll see sales come in and
they've got the set of KPIs that they're
tracking you know lead response time
that that sort of marketing and customer
acquisition cost and every every
department has a set of management
metrics that they use to evaluate how
they're doing evaluate productivity at
scale and that so is super powerful and
engineering has been responsible for
wiring up
a lot of other industries too metric
serving management and yet it still sort
of the last frontier itself right like
there's not
you walk into a board routing or room as
a CTO and you're really in there sort of
telling a narrative account of some
stuff that shift and some stuff that
didn't and there's really no benchmarks
to compare this quarter to last word so
that's the problem we're really focused
on got you that sounds interesting and
it's really a problem that a lot of
engineering managers definitely are
dealing with yeah but what's the with
the I give us some more insight into you
know what's the way that you're looking
at it from from your experience yeah I
mean you know this is as many products
it was a initially product born out of
personal need I was an engineering
manager at startup he started with a
small team where we were very much in
kind of that GarageBand mode where you
know where every kind knows everyone's
doing it was fast we kind of make
decisions collaboratively and that was
scaled that team up to 10 15 20
engineers where we really started to
feel the pain of not having hard data
and the specific thing that you run into
as you started scale is that you know
everybody can't know everything anymore
and when you get to that point it's hard
to communicate with stakeholders you'll
get people who are walk into engineering
whether that's physically into the room
or metaphorically because you're working
remote and saying how is this feature
going and answering that question can be
super painful if you have a really big
team because it's just not obvious
there's no way to look into you you know
sort of a person's last two weeks of
work elegantly and say oh it looks like
they're making great progress or geez
they've been stuck for three days and
there's Brian and their gears on proper
so that was the data just for the
product and a lot of the things has
changed between they the way of doing
software development the lifecycle
itself has evolved and we we keep
hearing about Sprint's and like you know
getting teams more agile in delivering
value to their customers and validating
that feedback what were some of the ways
engineering teams organized and a
retrospective with feedback loops before
that that worked and and how is that you
are now yeah I think you know prior to
agile we there was this funny state
where you sort of ask engineering for
read of a big spec ask engineering to go
deliver on that and then you wouldn't
see him for three to six months if you
were lucky okay and and possibly longer
and then oftentimes the product came out
we're getting radically different
because you know no battle plan survives
first contact with the enemy that kind
of it
agile generally pretty awesome was the
idea of pressing those feedback loops
and and you know I think the fact that
that's become an industry standard shows
how valuable that is the thing that were
the thing that agile does really well is
a lot of support casting and making sure
that the stakeholders are read into the
decision-making and socializing
decisions as they happen
so there's not this massive disconnect
between engineering and stakeholders the
thing that the thing that has not yet
provided is a set of metrics to you to
say okay it looks like our team is doing
well right most of the agile metrics are
very are very based on self reporting so
a story point is this currency that
evolves over time for the team
but it's weird before to say let's go
increase the amount of story points
we're going right because everyone knows
that the easiest way to do that it's
just overestimate your tasks and every
time stakeholders outside of engineering
come in and say okay we're gonna
standardize on 40 story points per week
or something crazy it just doesn't
really go well because that's not what
story points are intended for and yet
there is still just a pervasive need to
have some tractable way to have that
conversation and say okay we want to
take major steps to improve our team how
do we do that and and we think that
that's sort of the next natural
evolution of of engineering management
and how engineering gets feedback you
have the challenge there has always been
that most of the easily harvested
metrics about engineering are not super
valuable so you know the sort of this
thing that everyone's worried about
which is that someone's gonna roll in
there and count lines of code and use
that as a proxy for value if it doesn't
work and we all kind of know it doesn't
work because sometimes the hardest
change is like a two line change
and so you know the real of the
challenge here is how do we how do we
develop a set of metrics that can give
us some accurate signaling for an
engineering team and help us make
changes that matter it's scale how do we
show you know if you've got a
stakeholder who who wakes up in the
middle of the night with a brilliant
idea you know a change to a product that
you're two months into building says
okay we gotta get this change in that
causes a lot of waste you know it causes
a lot of of damage to to engineering
ability to deliver and I think the
industry would be well served by a way
to quantify that waste like if you can
if you can do you know approach that
problem and say look we're happy to make
these changes but you have to understand
we just invested two hundred thousand
dollars of product progress on this if
we take a right turn here we're going to
be two hundred thousand dollars in two
months behind and here's a picture that
shows you this is basic facts on my
video so that's really our goal here is
to have feedback loops that are really
good for both for inside of engineering
and if you're communicating across these
organizational lines and helping people
understand what the work of doing a
software development slight so that
Travis you mentioned you know about
engineering teams organized for agility
and doing a lot of retro specs and
feedback loops before and how different
it is now but isn't everyone already
measuring against a common company goal
like why do you okay let me rephrase
that
isn't everyone measuring against a
company pool why measure engineering
differently yeah I think I think there's
value in doing both so you definitely
want to have everybody rallied around
common goals
you know that's independent of
engineering or anything else that's just
a good practice in addition to that it's
good to have a bunch of levers to look
at engineering and say okay here's the
areas where our team is super strong and
here's the areas where we can improve
without being able to to measure
engineering centric metrics it's just
really hard to figure out how to make
things better and that ends up having
the net effect of being a little
disempowering to the engineering
department as a whole so when other
teams are
are going into a boardroom with metrics
that say look we have improved in the
following three ways 20% in this area
15% here 10% here and now we want
Moorhead cap what that means is that
it's super easy for them to advocate
about what the ROI of staffing up their
departments and when you when you get
engineering coming there with only
narrative accounts you know no no real
tractable way to show the ROI of the
engineering team the unfortunate side
effect of that is you're basically
depending on on engineering managers to
be politically savvy which is not really
when engineers are at our best right
like we're at our best when we come in
there with a bunch of facts and data and
say you know we shipped shipped a bunch
of stuff we are slightly understaffed
here if you give us three Moorhead cap
you can expect us to ship this much more
stuff that's a powerful place for an
engineer because we're talking about
data and artifacts I see and you
mentioned otherwise just for the
audience can you clarify what that is
yeah yeah return on investment so so you
know if you're looking at a if you're
considering a request from engineering
like hey we need to go and do a bunch of
refactoring for a month here and if we
do that refactoring we're gonna move a
lot faster oftentimes what people hear
there is they hear the engineering lead
saying hey we want to do stuff that you
don't value for a month right because
this technical debt is really only felt
by by engineer the pain is only felt by
engineering and it's felt in our ability
to deliver stuff quickly but if you can
put up a series of reports and show that
the value of paying down technical debt
and sort of show technical debt being
paid down over a month is that
engineering moves a lot faster and is a
lot more lightweight and can deliver
stuff faster after we do that and kind
of again show that curve of of
productivity increasing after having say
a couple Sprint's to address a bunch of
technical issues that's super valuable
and it allows engineering to go and make
these agreements with the stakeholders
and with enos or maybe it's the product
team whoever is really wanting more new
stuff and say well what you buy by
letting us pay down technical debt for a
month here is the ability to get more
new stuff faster in the future and then
being able to back into that after
afterwards and show that yeah we are
actually shipping stuff 30% faster like
we said very very powerful right I see
some back you know some baseline and
effort estimation to be able to get to a
point where you can justify factually
with what the return on investment would
be for a particular effort whether it's
rewriting a particular piece of code or
refactoring an existing you you know
code yeah historical metrics are super
important just generally I mean you know
the you know all this stuff the very
first thing to do in there to do is go
in there and say okay how do we how do
we develop a baseline for how we think
about productivity you know there's some
oftentimes it's the initial step there
is some just very kind of like brushed
your teeth eat your vegetables type
metrics like engineers theoretically
want to be coding the organization wants
them to be coding so how many days a
week is an average engineer on this team
able to code and you'd be surprised that
it's not five generally yeah like
there's a lot of overhead it tends to go
into engineering it's more like two or
three and so take looking at something
like that and having the rest of the org
say oh my gosh when we call an all-hands
meeting with the engineers that has a
cost yeah and the cost is that they're
unable to do the thing which they're
amazing at I mean it seems ridiculously
simple but you know it's it's very
difficult to look at that and and so
what happens instead is that people call
these all-hands meetings everybody kind
of groans and knows that you know it's
not really great for for their own
personal productivity they rather be
coding but there's really no way to
advocate for hey maybe only call the
people who are necessary or instead of
having yet you know $100,000 meeting a
little bit of data in situations like
that goes a long way yeah I think that's
another experiential point of view that
people think in generating productivity
and measurement is an art in there is a
lot of science behind it but there's
also emotions communication tracking
involved and I see a point about you
know how meetings take over
a lot of that while you actually produce
real value real code yeah if you walk
into an engineering team and say alright
how many people went to CS school right
like everybody raises their hand we all
said well raise our hands yeah yeah we
all win
and and what you learn there is how to
create great great code and there's a
lot of artistry to that facet of it and
then if you ask that same group of
people all right how many people taught
you how to be effective in a work
setting how many how many of you in here
were taught like here's how you advocate
for stuff here's how you work well with
another group of engineers here's how
you deal with an obnoxious set of
requirements like put a mood button in
the app right and basically nobody has
ever been a been taught any of that
stuff it's really not part of the
curriculum is something you have to
learn on the job and and that's the
kinds of the kinds of things that we
like to surface is these sort of people
centric metrics like like one of the
biggest problems in in this org is just
that engineers are in a lot of meetings
and they don't get the opportunity to do
a lot of code big broad things like that
right and you have to justify or at
least create metrics that show how one
thing adds up to value versus another
yep it's reading that stuff all the way
through to and therefore this creates
value for the business is is really
where a lot of the work is right so I
actually went through the 2017 developer
productivity survey on on the blogs and
I believed that there was a global
survey at least in the North America and
in Great Britain let's just for for the
next couple questions I want to actually
go deep down in into what your main
findings were and then how did it
actually create more insights into
various things that engineering teams
should measure
definitely yeah I mean being sort of
start at the top here you know one of
the things that we a lot of this was
initially prompted by a product
development you know we we went and we
started with some very basic stuff like
do you know software engineering even
want metrics and and this there's an
overwhelming response in the affirmative
there everybody wants metrics they just
ones that are good and relevant and then
if there were good metrics they'd be
very interested in knowing them you know
one of the one of the really key
questions here was what slows you down
and like if you're if you're a developer
working in the industry what are the top
things that slow you down and a lot of
the responses there were waiting for
other people to do stuff so like like
human thread blocking right right and
the bigger the organization the more you
see this kind of stuff worth a JIRA
ticket sort of goes into this holding
state where you're waiting for approval
from legal or sign-off of some sort and
and then you know maybe you switched
focus and work on something else but
that actually soaks up a lot of time
task switching is super expensive you
know you can only track so many kind of
open items of time and so that was the
number one thing that the people replied
with you know and then there's there's a
couple others in here like meetings
inadequate tool sets and and by and
large we see that you know a lot of
what's slowing engineers down is stuff
that does not necessarily have any
inside engineering but in those boundary
lines in the hand-off places between
engineering and somewhere else and so
having data to communicate that that's
what's happening is pretty powerful
stuff right and the the point that you
mentioned about waiting on threads just
like in in software we've got a lot of
concurrency and and sequential stuff
that we build on is there is there some
insight into how tools or engineering
metrics can help bring those up um yeah
I think you know in general if you can
when you have an engineering team whose
time is being soaked up by non
engineering stuff there's really that's
not felt organization-wide it's felt by
the individual engineers who who-who
have to deal with that and then also get
all their deliverables done and so if
you can if you can quantify that stuff
and say look our our engineering teams
spent 30 percent of their time in
meetings or you know or whatever a bunch
of other overhead and and have that
conversation in a more objective way
that tends to be
that the situation tends to resolve
itself it D politicizes everything it's
no longer about somebody's opinion of
how they want to work it's about waste
happening that nobody really wants so
again and again what we see here is that
data is Engineering's friend no matter
no matter what that data is it is it
favors engineering because engineers
tend to be sort of facts driven people
you know we've all we've almost sat on
that we've all sat in that meeting where
as an engineer where you're sort of
getting out talks by the students right
like you know for a fact that something
this guy is saying is wrong and there's
just no way to communicate it is a great
there's a great YouTube video to this
effect where they're sitting in a room
and this guy is saying we need you to
make seven lines all perpendicular and
there's some insane well that doesn't
even make any sense right so over and
over there's this trend where facts are
very friendly to engineers because
that's sort of what we like to play with
it's the tools of the trade you know
engineering is very concrete thing to do
and so the more data we can bring you
into the equation when when we get asked
these two difficult questions like why
is everything late all the time like
engineers get asked that all the time
and and frequently the answer to that
question is outside of engineering right
it's not like everybody's sitting there
playing foosball that's that's sort of
what everyone wants to think and it's
just not true the answer is a little
more subtle than that right it's like
well because we keep shifting our target
or we're not even clear down here what
we're building like this the specs here
are so loose that they were just trying
to go off of the last thing we heard and
surfacing those kinds of of replies to
why is everything laid with hard data is
very very effective for helping engineer
play the elbe engineering play the role
they want to in the organization right
and I I think they the other point that
comes in here and that's one of the more
communication driven size driven impact
here on how other teams organized and in
the liver is the the size of the team
itself I've heard a lot of good things
about organizing companies within
different units of product engineering
sales or having very horizontal layer
teams with product engineering and sales
all part of the same track making
decisions faster everyone being in the
same room at the same time can can mean
more quicker decisions even even in the
DevOps world I feel that there is a lot
of value in making sure that teams have
a shared goal so that there's not any
one throwing decisions of the wall or or
you know accountability is is clearer
but at the same time you know certain
tasks get done faster than when the
teams are organized in in the right
manner how do you see that in in the
size of a company let's take an example
of a start-up versus an enterprise yeah
yeah sure I mean well when it comes to
two metrics I you know typically small
teams don't really need them I mean
we're a metrics company so maybe it
sounds weird for us to say that but a
really small team doesn't you're not
dealing at a point where that stuff is
relevant at all as a team grows the
reason the data starts getting
introduced into the equation is that
typically you know a team evolves a
little bit beyond say five or six and
there's a team lead suddenly we sort of
like we take one of the engineers and we
sacrifice them right they no longer get
to code and now they have to talk to
people okay yeah it happens over and
over and that person needs to have some
way to do that they need to need to
solve the two problems immediately one
is how do we communicate that we're
bringing value right like how do we how
do we show people that work is happening
down here before a feature ships because
sometimes that could take a while and
then the second is how do I as the team
lead here focus my efforts on a
day-to-day basis right do I just like go
randomly pick some commits or a PR just
kind of dumpster somewhat or can I be a
little more elegant and focus on the
stuff that really matters and so that's
sort of the first level of where
companies emerge into needing data is to
have just the touch of elegance with
regard to managing a team right like
what are the important things to pay
attention to you today I've got two
hours here to focus on help
his team succeed where do I put that
focus and then as T as teams were even
more you know into bigger and bigger
this enterprise setting really the role
the data plays there from what we're
seeing is large-scale change so if
you've got let's say you've got a new
process you know you want to roll out
agile so you do it across thousands of
Engineers and then you and then people
want to know how did that go we invested
a bunch of resources in rolling out
agile how'd that go and and we don't
have anything to report wreck it like
we've sort of report on our feelings
like everybody seems to be happier I
don't know some people are sad some
people are happy and and that's just not
it ends up sapping the ability to do any
sort of large-scale transformation and
engineering only gets small stuff right
so so what we see is is that large teams
use this when they want to go advocate
for say hey we need to introduce an
entirely new tool chain here and and
we're gonna do that work on a pilot
project and then we're gonna take these
metrics and see whether or not that's
making any improvement right right yeah
and then we're gonna come back and we're
gonna say okay well we got about a 5%
bump in our ability to get to ship
features that seems good the products
cost is less than that so we're gonna
roll it out broad so that kind of big
scale change for information whether
it's new tools or new processes needs a
feedback loop and and that's where
productivity metrics come in so we've
established the fact that visibility
into engineering is is a lot better when
we actually do it as a data science when
we actually do it measured with a
baseline in the nitrate upon it it's
it's also good for large-scale
transformations like you measured of
going like you mentioned of going agile
is a company and then with size the
importance increases what do you think
is is is more important from an
engineering managers point of view when
when when his or her team grows from a
size as you said bigger than five to
slowly start getting into
you know investigating into the more
critical baselines and then you know
building up those I wouldn't say those
metrics yet but East the processes to do
to get that cultural alignment yeah I
mean I guess the general you know
there's a lot of different starting
points and there's a lot of um ways to
be successful one thing that is sort of
generally true is that KPI spam is bad
so the last thing you want to do is go
find a bunch of stuff you want to
improve and introduce all that stuff and
if you can clarify what is a KPI oh yeah
sorry
so KPI key performance indicators so
people will you know this stuff gets
rolled out all the time people say hey
we're gonna target these these areas for
improvement and we want to see everyone
be better by the end of the quarter or
whatever so these KPIs key performance
indicators get rolled out say okay this
is what we're targeting for improvement
and and that's good you know that's a
good way to use data what what makes
that successful is focusing on one thing
at a time the important thing to
remember when using data for any kind of
like management or change stuff is that
that's something that everyone has to
pay attention to in addition to their
job like everyone has a full job they
got deliverables every day they're
responsible for all that stuff and then
any sort of global improvement is
another layer of overhead on top of that
and so you don't want to layer in like
15 things that we're gonna improve by
the end of the quarter because everyone
will just experience that as a total
beatdown and so what you want to do
instead and what we see successful teams
doing you're picking one thing that will
be a high-value way to improve improve
stuff like I keep coming back to this
example because it's a good one like
let's get everyone out of meetings and
back into the code let's try that for a
month and see how that goes and see if
we if that creates a change that we like
and so that could be you know that could
be a very simple kind of KPI like we're
gonna try to maximize the amount of days
that everyone was able to to actually go
in and do something in the code like
independent of whatever that is check
some code in because cuz that's what
we're all here for and that's what we
like doing so I guess the broad council
there is no matter what size team you
are if you're starting to do this data
stuff start really small you know
introduce something like some single
interesting thing ideally that everybody
that addresses a pain that the entire
team feels from from people outside of
engineering to engineers themselves and
then target that one thing for
improvement and then once that
successful move on to the next day but
don't go in there and spam out a bunch
of initiative stuff all at once or it's
just gonna create a lot of resentment
right so I think starting small
measuring it and then I trading upon
those indicators to create a sense of
small KPIs
yep I mean it's just like going to the
gym right like anybody can go to the gym
but the reason you hire personal trainer
is so that they can go in there and say
we're gonna work on your core first
right and not go in there and just have
a million things to do right it's really
about breaking this stuff up into
accessible chunks and making the problem
whatever that whatever the thing you're
you're working on something that is
immediately addressing one tractable so
Travis we talked about KPIs and we also
established how important it is to
measure engineering productivity both in
small teams large teams also during
transformations in to establish
baselines to be able to get a point of
view on how we have improved time over
time what do you think is is the measure
itself here how do you measure you know
the engineering impact and and we get
into the data aspect of it yeah I think
there's a there's a lot of ways to go
about that one of the there are a couple
interesting examples we can look at here
there's this great Sufi story about how
and there's no real how wisdom is not
universal right so if you look at like
if someone in the future came and they
found a like a is that the dsm-4 that
has all the prescriptions in it and they
look at that and they're like oh look
this is all medicine and and they didn't
have any contacts they could basically
start giving everybody medicine without
understanding the disease and and that
wouldn't work out really well so a lot
of what we we advocate for is how is
developing a set of metrics
that really address the one or two
things that your team is focus on so for
example we worked with one team that had
this problem where they were engineers
it sort of felt like all the engineers
were stumbling over one another and when
we looked in at their data what we found
is that there was this pattern it was
sort of a culture of shipping monoliths
so an engineer would go there like work
on something locally for a while they'd
have it out for a week or two and then
they would check in this big it was
shocking in one massive commit right
which would we should basically create a
merge conflict for like every other
engineer on the product and that was
super ineffective because you you get a
bunch of operational overhead and people
kind of stumbling over one another and
so we worked with those guys to say look
that you guys need to move more towards
this taking smaller bites methodology of
let's break all the work into pieces
check in you know five six seven eight
ten commits a day push that stuff so
that other people can rebase on it and
and have breakpoints here that that
provide a reasonable way to back out if
you run into a big conflict like
integrate your work more often so just
like you get people you know programmers
communicate at the level of code pretty
frequently and so if there's this big
gap between when you're communicating
this is what I'm doing literally at the
level of code not with words that can be
super problematic and so when we go in
there we'll look at our people just
checking in these whopper commits all
the time like is that something that
this team means to improve or are they
doing pretty good with granular delivery
so granular delivery tends to be a
really a really big theme you know
pushing stuff up to where where other
developers can see it and sort of
comment on it the way that people do do
code review are large bodies of work
getting sufficient code review or is
that stuff getting rubber stamped those
are all metrics that we tend to tend to
advocate that people look at and pick
the one or two that can address
something very immediate for the team
gotcha so this is more iterative in
approach to continuously check in small
amount of changes and
keep building upon it and integrating
with team but how did you get to to get
the team say agree upon the the number
of developers working in a certain you
know integrated manner and and not
having to go through a large
transformation or cultural change
journey and even if it was how did that
work out you mean going towards more
data-driven introducing data as as a way
to do management yes yeah that tends to
be there tends to be a first phase which
is largely observational so the first
phase is just to say look we've got this
tool it provides much data about
engineering it's just data let's look at
it and and the first step is to get a
baseline for where things are at so the
first step towards using data to make
life better is not using the data and
taking an observational stance and not
trying to go in there and make a lot of
assumptions and once you've got this
feel for for sort of what where the
team's at what normal looks like you can
say look it seems like this would be a
good area for for improvement what do
you guys think I mean we've seen a bunch
of teams roll this out and the first
thing you know the the best way to use
data initially is just to help
engineering get something it wants we're
an engineering is a team and you know
that could be hey we want better
requirements talks we hear that one a
lot like we want to use this data to to
help people understand that a more
fleshed out requirement stock leads to a
faster implementation so something like
that it's a great place to start right
and did that vary between the engineers
in the team like the rule they played
junior engineer senior engineers team
leads managers how does that visibility
matter to say a junior engineer versus
what the manager cares about yeah we we
focus a lot on team leads largely
because they have people problems which
is a lot of what we're a lot of what we
focus on meaning it's very hard to
figure out how to provide value if your
team lead to 20 people
you know who needs your attention today
if you if you think about walking into a
sprint or a daily stand-up everybody in
a daily stand-up tends to say like
here's what I'm working on but there's
no real visibility into whether that
person is stuck and has been grinding on
a problem for three days or whether
they're making a lot of progress so
having a data layer on top of that to
say hey look do you need a hand here
like it can it kind of jump in and get
you some resources can I can I ducky
this problem with you that's pretty
valuable as an engineering lead it can
be challenging to figure out how to be a
good actor because you have this double
blind you interrupting an engineer while
they're working is super costly like
you're holding these this glass palace
in your head of abstractions and trying
to figure out how to you know how to
write that up and then someone's
shoulder taps you and says how's
everything going very destructive but
not interrupting somebody who's been
stuck for a couple days and could really
use someone to talk over the problem
with is also fairly destructive and so
when you're a team lead it's just it's
very hard to calibrate on how to be a
good actor and you know JIRA just sort
of tells you where people are oriented
and it's a valuable tool to get a read
on what everyone's doing but it doesn't
really give you any insight into the
engineering pipeline and the flow of
work and that's really where where we
think that metrics are needed are you
mentioned Geena here and that's a very
important tool that a lot of teams not
just using JIRA but also very similar
task tracking bug tracking and and story
tracking tools you know being used in
more and more agile teams today how does
that translate into some of the
baselines that the the lead can get in
when it comes to stand-ups and in
tracking just the sprint delivery itself
I mean I think it's a it's an essential
tool at this point you know I don't know
if we've ever run into a team that
doesn't use some form of issue tracker
but you mentioned that there is no there
is no proactive visibility into how the
sprint itself is going and if there are
challenges yeah
I think a good metaphor might be you
know JIRA is kind of like the navigation
on your car tells you where you're going
gives you an estimate on when you're
gonna get there gives you some
directions sometimes you know provides a
lot of a lot like its navigation for
where you're headed it's not the
speedometer or the gas the fuel gauge or
the temperature gauge to see if the
engines heating up and all of those are
also needed if you're gonna if you're
going to be in the car driving in it and
that's sort of how this stuff plays into
a team JIRA is the nav it shows where
we're headed it shows when we expect to
get there but what it doesn't do is
allow you to figure out if the car is
healthy like if it's low on fuel are we
or people getting work too hard here or
are we understaffed that kind of stuff
is just it's not really a JIRA problem
well that's pretty powerful for a
software data design metric to work with
software engineers managers team leads
and gives that insight I'd love to be
like dig deeper into how do you get to
that meaningful data beyond the tools
that are used day-to-day in in our
software development life sure so one of
the things as an example one of the
things that we look at is coach earn so
coach earn is something that we might
not get and it basically you know it's
use amnon code example here first
imagine you write an email and you look
at the email and you're like this is no
good so you throw it out and you write
another email second draft you look at
that one you're like this is also no
good so you throw that out you write a
third email that's good so you ship it
we would say that there's three emails
were written one email was shipped and
there's this Delta of two churned emails
right which is interesting and so we
look at that at the level of code we
look at when engineers are sort of
rolling along there's this normal level
of rewriting your own stuff like we try
something it doesn't quite work out but
then if you if you see an engineers sort
of bobbing along and then there's a
massive turn spike that's generally a
leading indicator of a problem because
they're you know if they're if they're
going along in there there's
working in the codebase and all of a
sudden they're spending a week
refactoring stuff that they just checked
in that's usually a sign that something
is is wrong like if you look at that and
you say this person is not really
prototyping new features so what are
they working on are they having a hard
time like getting this thing in is it
it's a really loose definition on what
the problem is
so we look at that that's kind of the
you know you could think of that as like
the engine heat gauge right like how hot
is this particular leg of development
running another example would be we go
back into codebase and we look at
globally if you take a team of say 50
people
what percentage of code base changes are
aimed at refactoring the legacy code and
again there's this normal baseline team
soon to have a normal amount of like
yeah you gotta go in there tweak some
old stuff while you're shipping a new
feature but if that starts to climb
above above about 50% you run into a
really dangerous situation where if over
half of your focus in the code base is
refactoring old stuff that's just gonna
snowball until until all of it is
refactoring old stuff ready and so and
so what happens is teams getting this
weird cycle they start throwing
headcount at the problem because they
want to ship stuff faster but if if you
can't keep the level of just like
refactoring of legacy code below about
half that becomes problematic and really
the right thing to do there is to set
everything down do a large architectural
refactor so that that doesn't become
this little cost that you know death by
a thousand cuts
that everybody has to pay forward as
they try to shape a new stuff that
metric is pretty powerful if we can
actually start looking at radius coach
and as you mentioned through the commits
that are being made by engineering into
into a particular story is it just code
that you look at or are there other
behaviors that could be tracked through
the release frequency or other you know
meaningful data you know we look at it
in that example it's just code search
urns specifically when I as a developer
and rewriting stuff that I just checked
in so it's you know there's this notion
of authorship like whose code is it
but that's largely mine from version
control we do also look at a couple
other sources of data currently and
smidgen Rd stuff to look at a lot more
we also look at at the data from the git
host so we'll look at things like how
many people are being pulled in for code
review so if we look at a team of 50
engineers or something and we can see
that there are two or three engineers
who are always reviewing every PR that's
a huge bottleneck and and that happens
quite frequently right you get these
senior engineers who are always who
everyone feels like they have to have
that person's blessing so spreading that
out it's pretty valuable it's not again
it has nothing to do with like the nuts
and bolts of software engineering it's
more the operational in people side but
it's a huge opportunity for improvement
yeah and then we also look at ticket
data so we do we pull in data from JIRA
and we typically use that to think about
things this is not quite shipped to
production yet but I'll leak it we have
the one that we're working on currently
called ticket jitter and so this is a
way for us to quantify how much change
happens to a an issue so a feature of
your building while that issue is being
actively developed so we tend to think
of this as bad like the perfect
implementation path is you get this
requirement stock that sort of answers
all business logic and user go on coding
your menu no coding along your merry way
and and then at the end the feature
ships and everybody's happy with it and
any deviation from that is is a little
bit of brain damage and the most brain
damage is if you're working on a ticket
while the stakeholder on that ticket is
actively modifying the goal the the
requirements and moving the goal posts
and so one of the things that we look at
when we look at ticket data is a way to
quantify that and say this ticket had a
lot of jitter and that's why it's late
it's not late because the engineer was
sort of screwing around or or we didn't
prioritize it or whatever it's late
because the goal posts here we're a
moving target and we just kept coding
towards that moving target the entire
time this ticket was in process and
that's super wasteful and the number up
of times the change was you know fifty
deviations in here there's a ton of
commentary there's a ton of
clarification and so if we want to ship
stuff faster what we need is for that
stuff to be resolved before work starts
that's pretty powerful correlation
between you know commit frequencies and
how the ticket data is actually being
correlated with it
in fact that'll be basically become part
of my next couple questions as we move
along which is in other words how do you
build context for such a such an
insightful metric for the the
stakeholders that are involved in in
making you know higher level or lower
level decisions for the team so I'd love
to drill down more on a bunch of
examples where you mentioned gear you
mentioned shader you mentioned like
ticket data that would probably come
from something like Zendesk how does all
of that get seen together aggregated as
more of a productivity or or challenges
or a sense of improvement that we can
drive from there yeah I mean the short
answer here is pictures with you we do a
lot of work in in d3 where you know data
is one of our main focuses I know I
think one of the the things that we as
as people who work in engineering kind
of undervalue is the power of high
visibility stuff like over and over we
see value in regular in people who can
do regular updates they're visual so
like if you put together a release deck
and let's say there's ton of work that
goes in there but you screencap the
noticeable changes in the app and you
and you push that deck out say here's
what we shift and you do that frequently
that is so valuable and so we take a
similar approach when thinking about
productivity we believe that the best
way to communicate that stuff is with a
picture so if you've got like a bunch of
little bars and then you make a change
then you got a bunch of bigger bars that
tends to be good or if you can say you
know we hear these stories in from from
engineering teams where someone walks
into engineering and says I need a third
of your capacity for this project I got
some Imperial feature in
features are something we use internally
to talk about a feature that has like a
very powerful stakeholder that just sort
of comes in and says we're building this
now happens all the time
so so if you have someone who walks into
engineering and says I need third of
your your capacity to build out this
feature and you say okay great so you
put some people on it and then two
months later you're sitting in a meeting
and that guy's gone well you didn't
really give us a third right and that's
why we didn't get there if you can
pulled up a picture and say actually we
gave you thirty six point nine percent
of our total capacity measured across
these three different ways of measuring
capacity so you know we delivered here
like we're putting an appropriate amount
of attention on it again data has this
effect of depoliticizing everything so
so that's just a delivering data
insights through pictures and showing
like this is the work moving through the
pipe that's a lot of how we how we focus
on making this accessible to less
technical people well that's a very
powerful statement there data D
politicizing everything there's so much
in context that that applies to pretty
much everything that we do as human
beings in not just the software industry
but in you know an overall business
process management so so this was this
was pretty powerful I think I probably
love to put some links if you can
provide me about the dashboards and the
graphics that aggregate this type of
data into more of a demo video maybe
that a lot of engineering teams and
managers and and and you know every
individual that that cares and and is
going through such an impact would love
to have these absolutely so Travis
thanks a lot for sharing that aggregate
value and and the graphics that you can
pull from such an insightful data stream
that you're collecting from different
data sources on a day to day basis these
are all tools and metrics and processes
that we done through but this is really
very valuable data that helps make
decisions yeah yeah yeah it's it's been
a wild ride man
the are
big goal here is always to thread the
needle between like all of this data
which is super noisy and then business
value you know like how do you how do
you correlate that with business values
right there's a lot of times when
refactor or rewrite is an afterthought
or it's already happened or happening by
the time you discover why things are
late or or so complex you have already
ended up starting on that journey it
helps if we can actually cover up that
covers some of these examples on a
proactive basis what else do you think
can an engineering manager or the larger
engineering teams communicate around to
be more proactive with historic context
yeah yeah you know one of the things we
focus on a ton here is how you take this
giant wealth of data which is not
inherently all that valuable and get rid
of all the noise and find the signal in
there you know and and that stuff is is
pretty challenging I mean like you look
at the thing that businesses always want
to know is show me thread thread the
needle between all of this get data and
show me how where the business value
comes in and there's always this
disconnect between what engineering is
doing and how that translates to
business value so an example of that
that we always refer to internally here
is the green button problem so you've
got this let's say you throw in a JIRA
ticket the and you're like I want all
the buttons on the site to be green now
right and you look at it you're like
yeah that's probably I don't know
whatever little CSS change maybe it
takes a half a day and so that work gets
greenlit and then an engineer picks up
that ticket and because they're a good
engineer they pick up that ticket
they're like well the right way to make
all these buttons green is to go rewrite
the entire templating engine volume in
there because that's way overdue and we
need to do it and and and the reason
that they have that impulse is because
good engineers want to get in there and
and improve generally improve the
codebase for everyone but that stuff
there's often a massive Delta between
the the ticket that an engineer picks up
and how they approach it and what was
Greenland and so a lot of what we
provide is the ability to cast
stuff sort of while it's happening while
it's in the pipe if you look in there
and you're like there's this ticket this
is chair take if it's like I turn the
buttons green and I can see that that
guy's in there doing a bunch of
refactoring of lazy code and has been
for two days that doesn't really match
with my experience of turning button
screen and so being able to catch that
stuff when you're before you're three
weeks deep into this massive template
engine refactor and people are like how
the hell did we get here that's super
valuable right and and again all of this
stuff is everybody following the things
that make them great you know what makes
the engineers great is the ability to
tackle the real problem not just the one
that they were asked to tackle and then
what makes a team lead great is the
ability to get in there and say well
look I get it
let's go see if we can get some
resources to address this templating
things it's a nightmare but not right
now today make the bottom screen and
that prevents a lot it's like problem
interruption right you don't get to this
point where people are dissatisfied with
engineering and you generally have just
a much healthier dialog because people
are are able to communicate about the
actual value of of a task and and what
that looks like in the engineering
pipeline I see and the technical debt
aspect also comes up most often in these
conversations when when people have
historical context in the team I'm
especially interested in also knowing
how does this help new engineers when
they come on board and we're slowly
going towards the digital and the
Millennial context here too to
understand what is more productive at
this point in time versus sometimes it's
also about what is the right thing to do
yeah I mean so you know one of the
things that's kind of nice is we is the
ability to look at something that
happened a long time ago as a reference
point so everybody if you've been on a
team for more than about a year or so
you all remember that period where I
don't know maybe you had to deal with
someone else's code and clean it up and
it was a nightmare for a month so being
able to dive into data forensics and go
back and say what did that look like
like what what does it look like when
our team is gets tangled up in a really
deep
factor from the perspective of all these
metrics and if you can go back and find
these canonical examples for your team
of you know a month of brain damage in
March because we all got caught up in in
getting rid of angular and moving to
react or whatever it is then you can get
a feel for what that pattern looks like
when it starts to spin up again right
and you can head those things off and
say look it seems like we're getting and
snared in another one of these issues
let's figure out whether or not we
actually want to tackle that now or just
get this deliverable off and then you
know do it in a month or something right
right and also yeah you mentioned
something about dignifying for the sake
of providing rewards at an individual
level
that's something I've seen before with
some CI tools you know and how different
badges in rewards get accumulated with
unit test coverage and like how
frequently are you checking something
the only thing I was like looking at in
in that sense was does this measurement
continuously improve the team as a
collective versus an individual you know
with some more positive reinforcement
and you clarified that it's more of a
collective team effort and you want to
make sure that you're making these
decisions together with factual data our
general approach here has not been so
much to focus on the individual engineer
you know what we don't want people
obsessing about this stuff
in fact we've strayed away a little bit
from from any kind of gamification for
the individual because it's it's the
beginning of a sometimes the beginning
of a disturbing trend it's like a thing
that kind of lends itself to abuse right
like you don't want to infantilize your
workforce like work like games are
awesome I love games but there's this
other component of work which is
distinct from that and everyone's trying
to kind of rally around a work goal and
and it doesn't need to be dressed up as
as a game of 5 metric so we've tended to
resist that and focus more on on metrics
it's like how do you if we presume that
there's a manager a team lead here who
really wants to empower their team and
find out what's blocking the team and
find out what's holding them back and
get rid of all that stuff
what metrics would we build them and
that's entirely where we focus and so
from our view a new engineer to your to
your question here a new engineer coming
into a team what they would experience
in a team that has really robust metrics
is they would have a lead that had a
pretty darn good idea of one where they
could jump in and provide value like
here's where our team is a little weak
and we need you to shore that up and
then to how to onboard them quickly like
they wouldn't know what good onboarding
looks like because they would have this
history of people who were on board it
well what that looks like and what areas
of the codebase they were in how we did
that you know a lot of a lot of how the
individual engineer experiences value in
a in a data-driven management setting is
by managers doing less damage that's
kind of maybe that's the the take-home
point here is ideally what we're doing
is improving a managers ability to kind
of get out of the way and get other
obstacles out of the way on behalf of a
team and so it's not really a direct
consumption value by an individual
engineer because that stuff can get a
little weird right
like if someone comes in and says hey
what I really need you to do is check in
ten more lines of code on average every
day you're like ok I'll make my methods
longer that's just not no that's not
really the pattern we want to encourage
totally yeah in you know I think earlier
in the in the session we were talking
more about how small teams and large
teams look at metrics differently look
at productivity in a different manner
there's also a lot of data that gets
generated with tools and processes as
individuals create more and more value
driven you know Sprint's how does the
the overall model work when the team
itself is totally the more like where
are there certain specific examples that
you can bring on for just remote teams
yeah ideally yeah you know that the way
that the individual narrative gets
brought in there is like is is asking
questions like well you know when is
when is Bob kick and buy when is he at
his best
and how do we get in review more of that
stuff because generally that tends to be
a really good outcome for everyone yeah
definitely
we are we tend to be a big fan of the
idea that remote can be just as
successful as on-site you know the
reason for that is that just because the
developer is sitting in a chair doesn't
mean you know anything at all about what
they're doing developer sitting in the
chairs staring at a screen serving
Reddit looks exactly like a developer's
sitting there you know cranking code so
so the this impulse to get everyone in a
room is not necessarily inherently
valuable the real value comes sort of
orthogonal to that which is like
defining things really well
like you know remote teams benefit a lot
from metrics driven environments because
you can answer for deliverables you can
answer for if you've got if it's very
easy to go look at what you know the
guys over in Europe did before you got
up it's just trivial that's great
you know without without metrics tool
that can be very hard to do if you wake
up and you got a team of 20 and they're
all in Europe and you're in San
Francisco and you want to figure out
like what did they accomplish today
that's actually just a hard thing it's
very simple it's a very simple question
it should be very trivial to answer but
it's not because the tool set that
allows you to kind of you know get a
feel for that the radar doesn't really
exist and so that's the value more than
anything else that remote teams
experienced row data driven stuff is
that you know it just gets incorporated
into into the workflow and and I think
remote teams and on-site teams benefit
about equally from having from having
less interruptions and having data be
the thing that drives everybody's
feeling of whether or not progress is
happening you know if you can oftentimes
the remote teams are into this challenge
which is like why I just can't tell if
they're working I think that's what
everyone worries about with remote teams
like are they doing anything over there
and if you've got a set of data that
says yes that is that's great it just it
just totally solves that problem right
and they also leads us into a pretty
interesting view on on Netflix overall
for engineering teams we talked about
engineering impact in general there's a
lot of you know measurable business
objectives or okrs that that the team's
own from larger company goals how does
the heart of the VP of engineering see
that metric ways to say in HR or a
business stakeholder that's basically
running a revenue number on it so I want
to understand more from from these
different roles how our metrics play a
role yeah
currently we serve the we serve
engineering and so our view of the
appropriate consumer for data about
engineering is somebody within
engineering and what we would ideally
like to see is that the VP of
engineering if HR is brought into the
equation it's because the VP of
engineering brought them in not because
they're sort of self-serving on a bunch
of data right so we like to see his is
engineering lead discussions about
engineering data that tends to be a
pretty healthy pattern I mean it doesn't
even matter if it's engineering centric
right like you don't really want your HR
team going in there and staring at your
at your sales data otherwise they'll
start to you know I don't know think
nasty thoughts about the week or
something I mean I mean there's some
there's some great HR use cases but in
our view that stuff tends to be very big
picture strategic stuff and not like
tactical metrics and so the ideal way to
present that is more in like the the
boardroom context where someone from
engineering has gotten together a bunch
of a very useful data put that stuff
together in a consumable slide deck and
then it's shared with the rest of the
org as opposed to somebody from outside
engineering self-serving data about
engineering right that's a pretty
powerful way to take some of these
engineering metrics into a more
strategic new point when when generating
say factual and reasonable arguments
yeah definitely you know we've seen this
we have this impasse
which you're referring to which we have
developed that takes a lot different
stuff from the codebase in doing out and
what we're trying to - were measuring
there is it's a proxy for movement in
the codebase like how much how much code
are we pushing around not a lot just
lines of code but like you know are we
are we editing a lot of different stuff
or are we are these big broad changes
are they are we hitting fundamental
parts of the codebase here and so when
we look at that and we look at kind of
the overall activity of engineering we
can use that as a bellwether metric to
see how successful engineering is in
moving the codebase forward just kind of
in bulk so using that as a bellwether
metric is very effective and the way
that that's used typically is people
will go in and and advocate against for
a particular tool tool chain and say
look we need to bring in certain CI and
whatever else right we need to bring in
this entire tool chain and if we do that
we're gonna get a massive bump in our
ability to ship stuff and if you go in
there and you measure something like
engineering impact and show this is
before this is after you know typically
what we see is when people are have the
ability to measure to to measure
engineering work in aggregate and take
measured steps to improve it we
typically see about a 20% boost in
engineering productivity over the first
six months and it doesn't really matter
how you measure that boost you could
measure it in less employee attrition
you know in general if you if you target
something very specific the effects of
that are spread across whatever kpi's
you may be looking to improve right have
you seen in generating especially you
know with with the impact in general
going into to cause a strategic change
in direction beer technology evaluation
or or change in product or or
specifically anything that has to do
with how the company looks at revenue
generating values yeah well we typically
stay away from things like code
complexity metrics you know there's a
bunch of companies out there
climate and some others that do a really
good job of that and so our focus is
really on the people what we want to do
is provide a deeper view into the team
as a group of people move and work
through the engineering pipeline so so
there's not there's a little bit of
automation around using this as a radar
tool like where should I be focusing my
attention we don't tend to serve up like
a ton of automated alerts because that
stuff becomes annoy see really fast and
instead what we do is give people a lot
of data at their fingertips to answer
the questions that to answer questions
as they come up like how's my team doing
Wow where can I weigh in today we view
ourselves as a as a tool for amplifying
engineering leaders as opposed to you
know we don't really want to automate a
way management we want to empower it and
and help it do things that are good
right it sounds like an important
company level or a strategic metric that
can easily be influenced by these
engineering metrics so thanks for
sharing that example you mentioned
something about the the systems or the
data sources that you collect the
information from I've seen a lot of
automation done as part of the software
development pipeline itself a lot of the
process and release management efforts
that are being made at this point in
time is to actually remove human
decision-making from the more day-to-day
repetitive tasks where it where exactly
is ordination coming into the picture
here in you know as you create sense out
of all this machine data so so our goal
you know with regard to add the
automation piece our goal is less to
automate away a particular part of
engineering or function there and more
to give engineering leaders power tools
to do their job better to make it easier
to gather the data that they want and to
generally be good right Thanks so I
think we've covered a pretty good amount
of metrics different data sources you
know how small large you know
medium-sized engineering teams can
actually use more and more of the impact
influencers and make you know tactical
and strategic decisions both for the
engineering teams as well as for their
organizations do you have
any best practices for both engineering
and business teams where they have
actually started measuring value or
improving efficiency and I actually look
at the word effectiveness more
importantly than just efficiency do you
have any such best practices just in
general from your learnings yeah I mean
again I think the the biggest thing is
to start small you know there's that old
joke how do you eat an elephant one bite
at a time
uh-huh over and over what we see is is
people who focus very narrow on
something to improve first especially
when you introduce a bunch of data
that's much much better than getting
kind of distracted and focusing on five
things at once you know again that it's
important to kind of keep that
compassion peace and remember that if
you're tart if you're saying the team as
a whole needs to improve across this one
metric that's the thing that people need
to pay attention to on top of their job
which is you know shipping deliverables
and writing software and all that stuff
and so you really can't expect people a
manager cannot expect an entire team to
track all the stuff they're tracking
it's just not fair right it's like it's
the team leads job to track all that
stuff and a lot of times the individual
contributors on the team they've got
their own job and so really you want to
keep all this change stuff as
lightweight as possible for the team and
and the way that we see people doing
that well is narrow focus you know do it
iteratively have a cycle where you focus
on one thing getting a pattern go in
there and focus on the next thing don't
create more overhead for your team oh I
see
I think we got some good you know this
practices here Travis I wanted to just
run that run through the the goals here
and see if we actually want to actually
add anything else that I haven't covered
here or if from your experience you want
to actually guide you know some of the
other things to look at so we did
discuss the the myths that engineering
productivity and value is is an art we
we actually looked at how some of these
challenges you know that the teams run
into in delivery pipelines and measuring
feedback loops can actually be driven
through very hard core metrics there are
systems process and tools driven also
you you covered ensuring productive
in metrics in general for different
sizes of teams and how KPIs can help you
know evolve as the team grows into into
different areas within an organization
and some of the best practices for for
the leaders involved in improving
effectiveness of all of these processes
that are being put in place is there
anything specific to the the software
delivery that you'd want to add here I
mean not really we covered a lot of
ground there I think you did a pretty
good job yeah awesome thanks a lot for
that I think there's a lot of you know
current and evolving trends that we kind
of saw here and I'm really looking at
putting in some links for for the
audience here just so that they can see
some of the demos also of how the
metrics you know get get - boarded the
graphs that can actually show some
aggregate value here and make insightful
decisions helpful yeah definitely in
fact been and probably has some there's
some really good resources for you
should follow them alright and and just
for the audience minister there's also a
co-founder and get primed with Travis
works so what's what's your go-to
reference for all things engineering
where you go for learning more about
what kind of data should you dig in and
start you know figuring things out in
more evolving trends
I mean shameless plug here I actually
get a lot of that from our newsletter
which is which is pretty good you know
if you want to check out we do not
shamelessly plug ourselves or anything
we do we do try to roll up industry
trend data and then you know typically
articles from other people or whatever's
hot at the moment shipped that
newsletter I read that thing religiously
you know other than that it's it's a lot
of a lot of the same thing everyone else
is doing I'm just looking at hacker news
isn't that kind of stuff yeah link to
the newsletter here so I know you blog
on get Prime is there any other way
audience can reach out to you yeah I
mean if they you know the best way to do
that is if you want a little tour well
we're happy to do that stuff you can
grab a demo on our site will provide a
bunch of links here and then I'm always
on Twitter if you want
directly I'm Travis Kimmel on Twitter
I'll put your handle there
thanks a lot Travis for for sharing this
insightful you know journey with us on
how you've learned you know basic
engineering metrics and and the the art
of measuring it and improving upon this
I'm sure the you know everyone has
learned a lot in in this particular show
so thank you absolutely it was great
talking with you thanks for your time
thank you for software engineering video
this has been Kishore Padilla thanks
thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by at
your police software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening